<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kate Salama M.D.</title>
    <description>Reproductive Psychiatrist</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2021 13:21:10 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2021 13:21:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.1</generator>
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Women's Neuropsychiatry Book Chapter</title>
          
          <author>drkatesalama@gmail.com (Kate Salama M.D.)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Dr. Salama is first author of the Women’s Neuropsychiatry chapter of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Neuropsychiatry-Behavioral-Neurology-Principles-Practice/dp/1260117103/&quot;&gt;Neuropsychiatry and Behavioral Neurology: Principles and Practice&lt;/a&gt;. This chapter discusses some of the sex-based differences in neurologic and psychiatric disorders. The psychiatric disorders discussed are those that are related to, or influenced by, the reproductive events in a woman’s life including perimenstrual disorders, perinatal disorders, and perimenopausal disorders.&lt;/p&gt;


          </description>
          <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/literature/2020/06/21/womens-neuropsychiatry.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/literature/2020/06/21/womens-neuropsychiatry.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>literature</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Perinatal Anxiety Screening</title>
          
          <author>drkatesalama@gmail.com (Kate Salama M.D.)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Dr. Salama (formerly Lieb) is the first author on this &lt;a href=&quot;/perinatal_anxiety_screening.pdf&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; published in the American Journal of Obstetrics &amp;amp; Gynecology MFM. It assessed the utility of adding perinatal anxiety screening to existing depression screening and found that screening for perinatal anxiety may increase referrals to mental health professionals and may be particularly useful in populations with a history of mental health diagnoses or substance abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/literature/2020/05/20/perinatal-anxiety.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/literature/2020/05/20/perinatal-anxiety.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>literature</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Inpatient Hospitalization for Postpartum Depression</title>
          
          <author>drkatesalama@gmail.com (Kate Salama M.D.)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;This article published in the Harvard Review of Psychiatry explores the case of a 28 yo female, 4 weeks postpartum, who is psychiatrically hospitalized for postpartum depression. Dr. Salama served as an expert consultant on traumatic childbirth. She discussed how to elicit a history of traumatic childbirth and explored the connection between negative perinatal and delivery experiences and postpartum depression&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/inpatient_ppd.pdf&quot;&gt;Journal Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/literature/2020/05/12/inpatient-ppd.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/literature/2020/05/12/inpatient-ppd.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>literature</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Women’s Health During COVID-19</title>
          
          <author>drkatesalama@gmail.com (Kate Salama M.D.)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;h4 id=&quot;how-is-this-pandemic-uniquely-affecting-women&quot;&gt;How is this pandemic uniquely affecting women?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has created a variety of new challenges that disproportionately affect women. Women hold the majority of essential jobs and may face a dilemma between greater viral exposure from continuing to work and loss of income and benefits if they don’t. Mothers who typically work outside the home are now faced with the impossibly challenging task of attending to and educating their children while attempting to maintain their professional productivity. With partners isolated at home, there is a concern for increases in domestic and sexual violence. Reduced access to family planning services and safe abortions coupled with resources diverted away from reproductive health care could be catastrophic for women and widen disparities in maternal health outcomes and gender economic inequality.
At the same time, this crisis has highlighted many enduring social and economic inequities. The preexisting wage gap and higher proportion of women in minimum wage jobs puts them at higher risk financially during this crisis. There are many more single mothers than fathers in the US who are now deprived of their social support and may be faced with having to leave their jobs in order to provide childcare. Women also assume most of the unpaid childcare, domestic, and eldercare responsibilities, including the emotional management of the household. This undervalued labor, which has only grown during the quarantine, leaves women fatigued and burnt out, and further entrenches gender inequality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-issues-are-presenting-for-women-who-are-pregnant-delivering-or-postpartum-right-now&quot;&gt;What issues are presenting for women who are pregnant, delivering, or postpartum right now?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women attempting to conceive, pregnant women, and new moms are facing unprecedented practical questions and emotional challenges during an already vulnerable period. While much of the data we have so far about coronavirus in pregnant women and infants is reassuring, we don’t yet have enough research to make sound, evidence-based decisions. Couples going through fertility treatment are facing postponements, cancelled cycles, and the uncertainty of when they’ll start up again. Couples trying to conceive naturally wonder if it is safe to continue. Pregnant women have had to adapt to virtual prenatal appointments, baby showers, birthing classes, and doula support. Hospital guidelines and restrictions regarding support and visitation are constantly evolving. Women fear delivering without their partners and needing to separate from their babies after birth. Many women find themselves grieving the loss of the pregnancy or beginning of motherhood that they envisioned, as the pandemic has stripped them of their sense of safety and security, as well as their social support, in a time that can already be quite isolating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-recommendations-do-you-have-for-managing-anxiety-and-isolation-during-the-pandemic&quot;&gt;What recommendations do you have for managing anxiety and isolation during the pandemic?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be helpful to simply acknowledge that this pandemic can bring up many perfectly appropriate and normal emotions including sadness, fear, anxiety, and grief. Sometimes just naming the emotions you are experiencing creates enough psychological distance to take away some of their charge. The 5-4-3-2-1 grounding exercise (name 5 things you can see, 4 things you can feel, 3 things you can hear, 2 things you can smell and 1 good thing about yourself) is a really helpful skill to
practice staying in the present by naming things that are certain, in a time when uncertainty is perpetuating anxiety. It is important to recognize that two seemingly opposite emotional states, like gratefulness and grief, can exist at the same time. You can simultaneously consider yourself lucky AND allow yourself to feel disappointed and frustrated. When feeling overwhelmed or anxious, remind yourself that while it seems like we are on the millionth day of a never ending quarantine, this period in our lives is, in fact, temporary. While life may never be completely the same, we will get back to being busy outside the home and feeling physically connected to others once again. It can be comforting to reflect on other times in your life when you went through periods of uncertainty and identify the strengths and character traits that allowed you to get through those periods. Online content, such as games and puzzles, gym and cooking classes, and even concerts and art exhibitions, can be used to increase pleasure and promote connectedness throughout the day. If the anxiety, loneliness, or sadness you are feeling is concerning to you and impairing your ability to function, it is a good idea to seek mental health care.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/literature/2020/04/30/womens-health-covid.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/literature/2020/04/30/womens-health-covid.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>literature</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Best Perinatal Depression Screening</title>
          
          <author>drkatesalama@gmail.com (Kate Salama M.D.)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;This study was designed to assess whether depression screening via a self-administered PHQ2 versus a nurse administered questionnaire is feasible in a prenatal care setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/perinatal_depression_screening.pdf&quot;&gt;Journal Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/literature/2019/01/02/perinatal-depression-screening.html</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/literature/2019/01/02/perinatal-depression-screening.html</guid>
          
          
          <category>literature</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
